When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that those who stay hydrated
tend to maintain a healthier body weight?
But is it cause and effect?
Here’s our first story.
In my video series
starting with
"How to Get the Weight Loss
Benefits of Ephedra
Without the Risks,"
I noted how drinking water
affects the release
of the adrenal hormone
noradrenaline,
making it the safest metabolic
booster for weight loss,
and recommended drinking
two cups (0.50 L) of cold water
on an empty stomach
a few times a day,
ideally before meals,
as a form of that
negative calorie preloading,
as I discuss in my video
"Evidence-Based Weight Loss."
But what about just
staying hydrated in general?
In a national survey,
one of the weight control
practices most associated
with successful weight loss was
"Drink plenty of water."
But it was also associated
with unsuccessful attempts
at weight loss.
It's just one of the most
popular weight loss tips
across the board,
both in the mainstream media
and a common recommendation
given to patients
by their physicians.
But does it work?
Can we just add water?
About a dozen studies have been
published on the matter,
and overall,
there does appear to be
a weight-reducing benefit
to increased water consumption.
What's the obvious confounder,
though?
Confounding factors, also
known as "lurking variables,"
are some third element that ends
up being the true explanation
for a supposed link
between two things.
Here's a textbook example:
There may be a tight correlation
between ice cream sales
and drowning deaths,
but that doesn't mean
ice cream causes drowning.
A more likely explanation
is that there is
a lurking third variable—
like hot weather, summertime—
that explains
why drowning deaths are highest
when ice cream consumption
is at its peak.
So, what might be
a confounding factor
that offers
an alternate explanation
of why those who drink more
tend to lose more weight?
Maybe it's because
those who drink more water
tend to drink less soda.
So maybe the reason
more water is associated
to more weight loss
is because
there's a third variable,
a confounding variable,
like less soda consumption
connected to both,
and that's the real cause.
The primary reason
that the CDC, USDA,
American Medical Association,
American Diabetes Association,
American Heart Association,
and American Academy
of Pediatrics
all recommend drinking water
for weight management
is as a replacement
of beverages with calories.
Even replacing
one sugary beverage or beer
with water per day
is associated with a lower
incidence of obesity over time.
American children and
adolescents drink so much soda
that replacing all
sugary beverages with water
could result in an average
reduction of 235 calories a day.
And what about exercise?
That's another obvious
confounder candidate.
After all,
who drinks lots of water?
Those who spend hours
working out.
So, it's no wonder
water drinkers might be slimmer.
A study
of dieting overweight women
took both soda and exercise
into account
and still, however,
found a benefit associated
with increased
water consumption.
Over a year, those who drank
at least a liter of water a day
lost about five more pounds
(2.30 kg) on average
than those who didn't.
The researchers were able
to control for physical activity
and intake of other beverages,
but what about other foods?
It turns out that
those who drink more water
also tend to eat
more fruits and vegetables,
greens and beans,
and whole grains,
and less total sugar,
and less fast food.
No wonder
they're a healthier weight.
To control for dietary factors,
the scientific world had
to bring out the big guns,
Harvard's big cohort studies
that followed
the diets and health
of more than 100,000
doctors and nurses for decades.
They were able to control
not just for other beverages
and lifestyle factors such as
exercise, smoking, sleeping,
and TV watching,
but a wide range of healthy
and unhealthy food intakes
from fruits and vegetables
to meat and candy consumption.
They were the first to show that
"increasing water intake per se
was independently
and significantly associated
with less weight gain"
over the long term.
Consumption patterns
in these studies
were by self-report, though.
Participants were just asked
to fill out detailed
questionnaires about their diet.
For more
of an objective measure,
researchers directly assessed
people's hydration status
by assessing their blood
and urine concentrations.
In both adults
and children,
the more hydrated people were,
the less likely they were
to be obese.
Spot-checking urine from
nearly 10,000 men and women,
researchers found that
nearly half of obese individuals
were walking around
under-hydrated
compared to fewer than
one in three individuals
who were normal weight
or lighter.
The problem with
snapshot-in-time studies
is that you don't know
which came first.
Did under-hydration
lead to obesity,
or did obesity
lead to under-hydration?
At a heavier weight,
you actually need more water.
The daily water requirements
of a man of average height
weighing 210 pounds (95 kg)
may actually be four cups
(0.95 L) more
than the same man
at 160 (73 kg) pounds.
And who's more hydrated?
Those who eat
more water-rich foods
like fruits and vegetables.
There's that specter
of confounding again.
The only way to prove
cause-and-effect
is to put it to the test
in an interventional trial,
which I'll cover next.
If you randomize
overweight adolescents
into one of two groups,
in which they're either advised
to drink eight cups (1.90 L)
of water a day or not,
what happens after six months?
The first question
you always have to ask
with interventional studies is:
Did the study participants
actually comply?
Both groups started out drinking
around two cups (0.50 L) a day,
and so the study
was designed to see
if there was a weight loss
benefit of consuming
six extra cups (1.45 L)
of water.
Unfortunately, the difference in
water intake between the groups
came out to be less than
a cup and a half (0.35 L),
which wasn't enough
to show any benefit.
Only one or two teens
in the water group
reportedly reached
the target intake.
To improve compliance,
another set of researchers
asked kids to check their pee.
The group of overweight
9- to 12-year-olds
randomized to
the water intervention
were told to increase
their water intake
to the point their urine became
straw-colored (a pale yellow).
Still, not every kid complied,
but those who did
lost significantly more weight.
Inspired by these small pilot
studies and early successes
with school-based interventions
in Europe,
researchers launched
the most ambitious study yet,
involving more
than a million students
in New York City public schools.
They compared obesity rates
and weight gain
in schools that implemented
cooled, fast,
filtered water dispensers
compared to control schools
that hadn't,
and the increased water access
appeared to translate
into less weight gain and
lower rates of overweight kids.
In the very least,
we should stop prohibiting water
from classrooms.
The accompanying editorial in
the AMA's pediatrics journal
was entitled: "The Power
of a Simple Intervention
to Improve Student Health:
Just Add Water."
Couldn't that result
just be explained
by decreased consumption
of soft drinks?
The study was performed
a decade after
New York City schools
had already removed soda
from all the vending machines.
They still sold
low-fat milk, though,
and that's what
the researchers suspect
may account for their findings—
the 12 percent drop
in milk purchases
after the water machines
were installed.
Milk intake, like soda,
results in weight gain.
This is true for skim milk
or even just
straight dairy protein,
pure whey or casein beverages
without the sugars
naturally occurring in milk.
The increased fat mass
from drinking milk
may in part be from
the increased insulin secretion
caused by milk protein.
Even dairy industry-funded
studies have found
that drinking less
than a cup of milk (0.25 L)
with a low glycemic index meal
can exaggerate the insulin spike
as much as if you had just eaten
high glycemic white bread.
While milk can impair
fat burning,
water may have
the opposite effect.
To get to the bottom of the
water and weight loss question,
tightly controlled metabolic
experiments were performed
in which whole-body
protein and fat breakdown
were measured under
different degrees of hydration.
Well-hydrated individuals
experienced
the best of both worlds,
increased fat burning
and decreased protein breakdown.
The way the body responds
to high water intake
is similar to how it responds
to acute fasting,
a switching towards
fat as a fuel source
while trying
to spare the muscle.
These were proof-of-principle
experiments, however,
with limited
real-world relevance,
as the high fluid states
were induced
not only by having
the participants drink
10 cups (2.5 L) of water
over a 12-hour period,
but also by dripping
extra free water
straight into their veins,
and even giving them
an antidiuretic hormone
to cause them to retain
even more water.
There are, however,
mechanisms by which
our day-to-day hydration status
can affect our metabolism.
When we get dehydrated,
our blood volume
actually shrinks.
This drop is
detected by our kidneys
that release an enzyme
into our bloodstream
that triggers the cascade
that results in the formation
of a hormone called angiotensin.
Angiotensin causes us
to become thirsty
and constricts our blood vessels
to compensate
for the diminished blood volume.
(That's actually
how a popular class
of blood pressure-lowering
medications work.
The ACE in "ACE inhibitors"
like captopril
stands for
Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme.)
That's not all that
angiotensin does, though.
Drip it on human fat cells
in a petri dish
and they start piling in
more fat.
This may help explain why those
with higher angiotensin levels
in their bloodstream
tend to be heavier.
The thought is that
those who don't drink enough
end up with chronically elevated
angiotensin levels,
which can lead to weight gain.
The most convincing evidence
comes from genetic studies
showing that
those born predisposed
to higher angiotensin levels
are significantly more likely
to become obese.
We can keep our levels down
in the normal range, though,
by staying adequately hydrated.
Though many may distrust
the safety of tap water,
bottled water may be
no safer, cleaner,
or higher in quality than water
straight out of the faucet.
There are risks to drinking
too much water, though.
Even healthy kidneys
may only be able to handle
about three cups (0.70 L)
of water an hour.
Beyond that we risk washing the
electrolytes out of our brain,
with potentially
lethal consequences.
Can you just drink
a sports drink instead?
No; in fact, there
was a high-profile case
of a high school athlete
who died after drinking
two gallons of Gatorade.
Drinking too much of anything
can be dangerous.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.